<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "puppet-guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="puppet_software">
  <title>Puppet software</title>

  <para>
    This chapter illustrates how external software is
    packaged in RPM's. The sections show different pieces of
    software and the analysis done to figure out what needs
    to be packaged. All the external software needed for the
    standard services in our infrastructure environment is
    packaged in RPM's.
  </para>

  <para>
    This raises the question: why do we want to do this? Is
    it not much simpler to just do:
<screen>
&dev1p; <userinput>gem install gpgme</userinput>
</screen>
    The answer is: yes! But, we want a robust and controlled
    environment. What if we don't have an Internet
    connection, because the environment is labelled as
    <emphasis>mission critical</emphasis>, and no Internet
    connection is allowed? What if, we want to develop while
    travelling by air? Many examples can be given to show
    that it is sometimes necessary to have all external
    software preloaded on a local Spacewalk or Satellite
    server. In this scenario, we are independent and
    completely in control what software can be deployed on
    target nodes.
  </para>

  <para>
    During the development phase, we do have an Internet
    connection and load external software via the
    <code>gem install</code> and <code>puppet module
    install</code> methods. The trick is to put the right
    directories and files in an RPM. Be aware, this is an
    iterative process!
  </para>

  <xi:include href="puppet_software/stdlib.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  <xi:include href="puppet_software/mini_portile.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  <xi:include href="puppet_software/gpgme.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  <xi:include href="puppet_software/puppet_lint.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</chapter>
